so here look here's another proposition
you can think about what we've been
doing so far in some way okay you can
think about what we've been doing so far
in some way as trying to figure out what
the world is made of and to answer that
we have to think about what do you mean
by the world and what do you mean by
made of because those when you're asking
a fundamental question like that the
terms in the question have to be
specified with a high degree of accuracy
or you're just chasing you're just
chasing ghosts around so we could say
well on one at one level of analysis one
level of resolution is pretty obvious
that the world the objective world
whatever that is is made out of atoms
and Democritus said that a long time ago
in Greece right he was the first guy
that came up with the atomic theory but
he didn't say that the world was made
out of atoms he said that it was made
out of atoms and space and you think
well that's you know obvious it's like
no no no no it's not that obvious
because as soon as you have fundamental
particles and space you can array those
particles in space and you can array
them in patterned ways and the patterned
ways are real too the patterns are real
too so and without without the space you
can't do that so atoms plus space gives
rise to something else and really what
it gives rise to as far as I can tell is
something very much like information now
information is a very complicated idea
what information is but that's okay we
won't go into that at the moment to
think about music right music is like
atoms of sound right because they're
they're discrete quanta of sound
essentially they're rainout in patterns
across time and obviously the pattern
the music is is not just the note it's
the pattern across time okay so one of
the things we might say is that well
there's atoms in their space and there's
patterns
okay so patterns now what are the most
fundamental patterns okay so let's put
it this way we're gonna say well what's
your problem how to live in the world
what's the world well roughly speaking
the problem is how to live as an
individual in society and nature it's
something like that okay so then we're
gonna say okay if that's the actual
problem the first thing you have to do
to solve that is to conceptualize
society in nature and conceptualize the
individual so you have to represent them
somehow
okay so how should you represent society
and nature and the individual and the
answer to that is that's complicated
it's not obvious now we kind of know for
example that one way of representing
society is the dominance hierarchy you
know that's not only a way of
representing and it's a way of being in
this society right to talk about the
dominance hierarchies to represent it to
be in a dormant of turkeys to live it so
we can think about a dominance hierarchy
society is more than a dominance
hierarchy but you know that's not a bad
first approximation and then we can
think of the place in which those
dominance hierarchies exist we might
think well that's for lack of a better
way of conceptualizing its nature so
it's complicated because you can't
actually sum these concepts up in single
words as far as I can tell you have to
use an array of words and an array of
images because the categories are so
broad that you just can't sum them up in
a single concept okay so you can sum
them up with words and you can sum them
up with images and you can sum them up
with stories and and that's that's what
we do as people so the quest no so we're
gonna say well is that if is that the
fundamental question how to live as an
individual in society in nature it's
like well I don't know if it's the
fundamental question but it's our
fundamental question so fine we'll go
with that
I'll go back over this a little bit
later but all I'll start with this story
yeah okay so we go back to the
birthplace of civilization then we're
gonna tell the variant of this story
that was discovered in the late
18-hundreds it's a story about this
guard called time at or mardik so here's
the basic structure of the story you've
got two primordial gods now the way that
Mesopotamians conceptualized the world
is they kind of thought about it you
know how if you're out on a field it's
flat and you kind of look at the world
the world looks like a dome right that's
the sky on a disk so that's the
Mesopotamian world now it's kind of the
world as conceptualized by the people
who wrote Genesis as well it's a dome on
a disk okay so the disk is land and
underneath the land is water fresh water
why well if you dig down in the land you
hit fresh water and then underneath that
is salt water and how do you know that
well you know if you go out to the edges
of the land and you fight an ocean it's
salt water so that's the hypothesis okay
so now as far as the Mesopotamians were
concerned the salt water in the fresh
water were two gods
now what did they represent well one of
them was male and one of them was female
and the female one was the salt water
the male one was the was the freshwater
okay so now and they kind of
conceptualize that as a kind of a
formless chaos so you can kind of think
of that water mixture as the chaos from
which life emerged it's something like
that but it's also the case and we
should remember that well that life did
emerge from water and that without water
you don't live so it's not it's not a
stupid idea it's kind of low-resolution
idea so is this chaotic intermingling of
salt and fresh water so that's sort of
the idea there's a chaos idea lurking at
the bottom of that and so that's ab soup
and time at now the Mesopotamians don't
say much about ab soo and I kind of
think that I think maybe that's because
at that point society hadn't become so
highly structured that and and
long-lasting that that a great
representation of it had been formed I
don't think that happened until the
Egyptians but I might be wrong about
that but in any case the Mesopotamians
don't say much about apps ooh so what
happens is ty Matt's down there in the
depths sort of like the whale in
Pinocchio fact very much like the whale
in Pinocchio and absolute husband and
they're locked together in a sexual
embrace and so part of the idea here is
that well the union of opposites is
necessary before something new can arise
and that that union of opposites can be
conceptualized in some way sexually you
know using male and female because when
male-female come together something new
emerges out of that and that sort of
ideas like the matrix you know the
matrix of things that's the mother
matter mother things emerge out of a
matrix so so anyways absolute I'm out or
down there in the depths and they're
locked together in a sexual embrace and
they produce offspring and lots of them
so that's the initial world of the gods
now there's all sorts of gods they give
rise to and we don't know a lot about
them but I'm going to make some
hypotheses about the gods because you
might think well what the hell are gods
anyways you know and so I I think about
them as personalities their
personalities and their archetypal
personalities and so it's like well
Venus for example is the God of love and
I'll show you some pictures of Venus so
what does that mean exactly well it's
like a complex of things Venus is how
you act when you're in love Venus is
what people find sexually attractive in
women Venus is the the possession that
occurs when you're in love or when
you're really attracted to someone it's
all those things and so it's like a
force that can invade you it's a way of
perceiving it's a superordinate instinct
it's shared across not only human beings
but birds and bees as we all know so
it's this it's a transcendent property
and it it can take personified form
because it can inhabit you and so it's
this thing that sort of objective and
sort of subjective and it's also one of
the fundamental elements of the world so
you might say well
Venus for example and there's Ares
that's Mars so that's a God of War and
he's usually masculine and he's very
aggressive and so well he's like a he's
like the personality of warrior like
rage so so so I kind of think about the
gods especially the more fundamental
gods is something like primordial forces
and here's a leap and I don't know about
it but I think that it's a
recapitulation in some sense of
individual socialization so I think that
what happens to begin with is that you
know you're as you emerge as an
individual you start out in a chaotic
and unformed manner and then these
things come to life inside of you and
those things are these fundamental
motivational systems that we were
talking about and so they're the first
products of chaos and then those things
have to get their act together okay so
like I said that's a leap and I haven't
been able to completely fill in the gaps
there but in any case all these gods and
goddesses get created by time at a nap
soon right so then they're running
around causing trouble the first gods
they make a lot of racket they're doing
a lot of impulsive and crazy things and
they make a lot of noise and they're not
very cautious and they make a big
mistake they kill apps ooh and then they
live on his body now that's a weird one
name you think well okay what's going on
there well absolute mass keulen and so
the masculine thing seems to be
associated in some way with like God the
Father in the dominance hierarchy and so
what does it mean if he's dead it means
that all this chaotic activity that's
disintegrated has killed the structure
and so they're all down living on a
corpse which is not a good thing and
maybe they didn't know what they killed
and so so imagine they're careless
they're kind of clueless they don't know
what the hell's going on they break a
bunch of rules and they destroy the the
the orderly element of what initially
gave rise to them and then they live on
its corpse another way of thinking about
that is that that's what you guys do
you're living on a corpse you're living
on the corpse of the past
right and it's the consequence of the
activity of the dead and it's dead
because it's the activity of the dead
right I mean the library there's no life
in a library except for the people in it
the rest of its all ghosts so you're
living on the dead shell of the past
okay anyways these guards are all making
all sorts of racket and running around
and spinning up wind and dust and noise
and it's really chaotic and then they
kill apps ooh it's like mmm that's not a
good idea
so absence also ordered and so what
happens when you kill order when you
destroy order what happens up comes
chaos
that's what happened in Iraq for example
okay so time at comes up and she thinks
well I don't know about these things I
created it's like they're really noisy
and and annoying and careless and they
wouldn't killed absoutely she's like
he's my corn sardis necessary it's like
now for them they're gone I'm gonna wipe
them out sort of like God deciding to
wipe out everybody with the flood it's
the same idea these stories all came
from the same area right so it's another
representation of that idea it's also
kind of a vengeful god idea now you
might think well what about this
vengeful god idea it's like well do you
really want to have a god that's a
vengeful it's like that's a stupid
question because you've got one whether
you want one or not so I can give you an
example so let's think about New Orleans
right so New Orleans got hit by a
hurricane and it was a natural disaster
and it wiped out a big chunk of the city
right well no that isn't really right so
the Dutch live underwater basically
right the whole bloody country is below
sea level so the Dutch make these huge
dams and they maintain them like Matt
and here's the Dutch rule we're gonna
try to calculate the worst possible
storm that could possibly happen in
10,000 years and then we're gonna build
those damn dikes so if that storm comes
we're safe okay so what happens Holland
isn't underwater so there's no natural
disaster so let's go to New Orleans it's
like well why did New Orleans get wiped
out well there was a hurricane it's like
did they know that there might be
hurricanes yes did they know that the
dikes
big enough yes have they been
complaining about it for a hundred years
yes had there been things put in in
place to try to get the dykes better yes
did it work no why not because it's
corrupt it's a corrupt state now all the
money they pour it in there to help the
people after the after the flood that
didn't help them it just disappeared and
so you can't if the state is corrupt and
the individuals within it are corrupt it
means the structure the society is dead
it's a corpse and what happens when you
make a corpse out of your society a
corrupt corpse well that's easy
mother nature comes back and takes what
she has and then you think oh isn't the
world a terrible place it's like yeah
try not frittering away the money see
what happens it's part of it yeah it's
part of it so there's a whole tangled up
idea of murders and so forth we'll get
into that so anyway it's okay so time
has had it she said well these things
aren't worth preserving I'm gonna go up
and wipe them out and then everything be
nice and calm and peaceful again and so
the guards they get wind of this you
know and they're thinking hey this isn't
very good because like she's that's tire
mat we're talking about here she's
Mother Nature like in that in her
terrible sense and she creates
everything and she kills everything and
if he decides that were you know going
back to where we came from that's
probably what's gonna happen so they're
pretty I'm worried about this so they
get together in a kind of a council so
they're trying to organize themselves
say they get together in the council and
they think oh well what are we gonna do
about this and so they elect they take
one of their gods and they say you why
do you go out there and try to you know
keep time out at bay straighten her out
so one God goes out and has a big fight
with time at and comes back and he he's
all defeated and wiped out and that
doesn't work and so then they send
another God out and he's just completely
useless that doesn't work he comes back
and it's it's getting pretty damn
desperate there in the realm of the
original gods and so this is going on
for quite a long time and while this is
happening the gods are still marrying
each other and producing offspring and
so forth and one day this new sort of
God appears
the scenes and his name is marek and
mardik is he's a new thing they're not
really sure what to do with him and he's
got he can really hear and he can speak
magic words and so what he says magic
words the day appears in the night
disappears and so he's got the power of
speech that's a big deal and he's got
eyes all the way around his head he can
see everywhere it can really pay
attention so you know and he's big and
he's strong and he's tough and all those
things but the big things is he can
speak and he can really seek and really
pay attention so the gods think hmm well
he's kind of a new character we haven't
thrown anything like that at time at yet
so let's let's do it so they all get
together in their Council and they bring
Martic in and they say well you know
we're kind of thinking to be a good idea
if you went out and fought this terrible
monster right and he thinks well you
think that's a good idea but you know
it's me on the line here so I need a
price and so the price is you make me
the determiner of destinies now that's
an interesting phrase and we don't know
exactly know what they meant but it's
something like what I am that's Marduk
is now going to be the thing that
determines how things unfold so it's
sort of like I'm gonna be top god
you mean if I'm going off to fight time
at I'm top god in fact that's how you
can define top god top god is the god
that can go out and fight time at so the
other you know the other gods they're
not very happy about having to
subordinate themselves to mardet but
they think beats the hell out of being
eaten by time at so they say yeah yeah
if you win you get to be like top god
you you have the tablets of destiny you
can determine destiny fine fine so so
fine Martin goes off and he gets his act
together and he gets big net and he
prepares himself and he rides forward
and and encounters time at she's this
great big dragon like monster thing
that's her there on the on the right
left so you can see she's kind of a
dragon angel monster thing she's like
she is a monster and what she is is
really an amalgam of frightening things
essentially so and there's Marduk on the
right and he's gonna go give her a good
whacking and so he goes out there and
the first thing he does and this is
quite cool
encapsulate her in a net no so think
about that because she's basically
natural chaos she's the productivity of
natural chaos and so what Marduk does is
encapsulate her in a net that's like a
conceptual scheme right he puts he puts
boundaries around the chaos and that's
what mardik can do that's that's his
ability with his ability to speak in his
eyes and his capacity to pay attention
so whoopee
he encloses her right and so that's kind
of hard on her she can't get out of the
net and then he cuts her into pieces and
then he makes the world out of the
pieces and in fact one of Martok's names
is he who fashions ingenious things out
of the carcass of time at which is so
cool because it's a tool use metaphor
it's right how do you conquer nature
well you go in there and you you know
decompose it in many ways and you make
weapons out of it you make cool things
and that keeps it at bay and how do you
do that by speaking and paying attention
so that's what the Mesopotamians figured
out now they didn't know that that's
what they figured out because like the
idea was already there it was implicit
in the dominance hierarchy in some sense
but and they were observing the
dominance hierarchy and well they got
their Kingdom together they were
bringing tribes in from all over right
and all the tribes had their stories and
then on all those stories had to fight
and so that's like the Battle of gods in
the Battle of the gods in heaven all
those stories had to fight just like
Islam and Christianity and Catholicism
and Protestantism are all scrapping it
all for dominance now they're fighting
how do we make sense out of this mess
maybe take several thousand years
Mesopotamia gathered together all these
tribes and their stories and then the
stories fought and out of that fight
emerged this story and that was a good
enough story so everyone was happy with
it
and the story was sorry I know we have
to start the story was whatever mardik
represents that's top god and so what
did you represent vision attention and
speech and so the Mesopotamia has
already figured out everything else
should be subordinate to vision
attention and speech it's like good work
Mesopotamians
sorry it's my daughter she wants to pick
me up
hello hi there where are you ok but ok
bye alright so one final thing
the Mesopotamian Emperor our Emperor was
charged with the imitation of Marduk
that's what made him sovereign so so
it's not arbitrary like if he was going
to be sovereign and he was going to be a
good sovereign that meant he had to be a
good Marduk and we'll talk about that
when we meet again